Guide to the National Council of American Soviet Friendship Records TAM.134
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Council of American-Soviet Friendship Records
1919-1990
1943-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Thomson, Alan Craft, 1931-
National Council of American-Soviet Friendship (U.S.)
TAM.134
16.25 Linear Feet in 14 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 oversize folder.
The National Council of American-Soviet Friendship succeeded the National Council on Soviet Relations, founded in 1941. The NCSR grew out of the more overtly radical American-Soviet friendship movement of the 1930's, whose organizational center was the Friends of the Soviet Union founded in 1929. The Council, composed largely of professionals who were sympathetic to Socialism, believed that the USSR and the United States should join together in their common fight against fascism. In 1946, the House Un-American Activities Committee began a formal investigation of NCASF, and in 1947, it was indicted for failure to register with the Subversive Activities Control Board. Throughout its operation, the NCASF issued numerous pamphlets and bibliographies about life in the Soviet Union, as well as information on American-Soviet relations. The collection includes the correspondence of the NCASF's principal officers, publications, flyers, scrapbooks,and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Alan Thomson, Executive Director for the National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, in 1986 and 1991. in 1986 and 1991. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1986.003, 1986.029, NPA1992.004, NPA.2000.228, NPA 2204.070, and NPA.2005.226.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Administration; II. Activities; III. Scrapbooks; IV. Photographs and Graphic Material.
Folders are generally arranged chronologically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
The National Council of American-Soviet Friendship succeeded the National Council on Soviet Relations, founded in 1941. The NCSR grew out of the more overtly radical American-Soviet friendship movement of the 1930s, whose organizational center was the Friends of the Soviet Union founded in 1929. The Council, composed largely of professionals who were sympathetic to socialism, believed that the USSR and the United States should join together in their common fight against fascism. In 1942 the Council sponsored a well-attended Congress of American-Soviet Friendship which was effective in recruiting celebrity sponsors, speakers, and supporters such as Franklin Roosevelt, Cordell Hull, Henry Wallace, and William Green. The success of the Congress inspired Dr. Harry Grundfest, Dr. Corliss Lamont, George Marshall, Reverend William Howard Melish, and William Morris Jr. to pioneer a permanent organization the following year.
The NCASF enjoyed widespread success under the chairmanship of Corliss Lamont. Almost immediately, more than 30 local affiliates sprang up across the country, including the very active American-Russian Institute in San Francisco and the Los Angeles Society for Cultural Relations between the US and the USSR. The program of the NCASF emphasized cultural interchange and education as a means of strengthening the bonds of understanding between the American and Soviet people. The Council set up special committees, such as an Architects Committee, a Committee on Education, a Women's Committee, and a Committee on the Arts. These committees sponsored various conferences and exhibits, such as the American-Soviet War Exhibit, shown at the Museum of Science and Industry in 1943 in New York City, and an exhibit of Soviet Architecture and American Housing and Planning. The Council also sponsored an exhibit of paintings by Soviet children at the Museum of Modern Art and an exhibit entitled "Soviet Artists and the War," held at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. In the mid-to-late 1940s, the Council held annual mass rallies in Madison Square Garden.
In 1945, Reverend Richard Morford became the Executive Director of the National Council, and remained in that capacity until 1981. Beginning in 1945, the radical post-war shift in American foreign policy brought the Council under increasing attack. In 1946, the House Un-American Activities Committee began a formal investigation of the National Council, and Lamont and Morford were cited for contempt of Congress. In 1947, the NCASF was indicted for failure to register with the Subversive Activities Control Board. In 1950, Morford was again charged with contempt of Congress and spent three months in jail. In 1951, the Supreme Court ruled that the Attorney General acted arbitrarily and illegally by placing the Council on the List of Subversive Organizations. Three years later, the Subversive Activities Control Board again declared the Council a "Communist Front", and the Council initiated proceedings against the SACB. During this period, the number of local affiliates shrank to three. In 1989, the Council again had to resume legal defense when the NCASF's executive director, Reverend Alan Thomson, was indicted by the federal government for bringing funds from the Soviet Union into the United States.
The Council has consistently denied accusations that it is a pro-Soviet organization, while claiming to be non-partisan. Some prominent leaders and members, such as Rockwell Kent and Elizabeth Moos, opposed the Council taking political positions in any matter. However, the Council has asserted its political outlook on a number of issues, opposing the 1961 US-sponsored invasion of Cuba and the Vietnam War. The Council also actively supported broader-based US movements for disarmament. With the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, the Board of Directors was bitterly divided, since Richard Morford condemned the action of the Soviet government. The political perspective of the NCASF was a varied mix of left-oriented politics: leaders, associates, and rank and file members held both pacifist and communist viewpoints. Throughout the Council's history, progressive religious leaders and churches have strongly supported the work of the Council. In the 1980s, this base of support expanded with the Council's efforts to broaden the issues of American-Soviet cooperation.
Many of the Council's activities have been educational projects. The Council sponsored numerous conferences and lectures on American-Soviet Relations, such as two held in 1951 entitled "From Bombs and Death to Cooperation and Peace" and "Facts, not Fiction--The Soviet Union Today." The NCASF initiated other programs to counter American anti-Soviet propaganda, such as the 1986 protest of the American film, "Amerika." The NCASF issued numerous pamphlets and bibliographies about life in the Soviet Union, as well as information on American-Soviet relations. Some of the titles are "The Story of American-Soviet Relations," by Harry Ward, "Soviet Education Today and Tomorrow," by Elizabeth Moos, and "Lenin's Humanity," by Howard Parsons. The Council initiated widespread distribution of Soviet films and documentaries to their local affiliates and to schools.
The Council has sponsored a variety of cultural activities, such as a Russian Music and Dance Festival in 1959, the Moscow Art Theater in 1965, and a gospel concert in 1986. The Council organized testimonials for notable people involved in the cause of American-Soviet relations, such as a ninetieth birthday party for Harry Ward in 1963, a celebration in 1965 for Richard Morford's twentieth year as the Council's executive director, and a John Reed Centenary in 1987. These events satisfied the NCASF's program for cultural activities in addition to raising Council funds.
The Council believed that their most important project was to promote cultural exchange at the local level. Since the late 1940s, the Council arranged individual and group tours of students, workers, and professionals to the Soviet Union. Beginning around 1970, the Council arranged several "Goodwill Delegations," in which small groups of Russians would visit one of the NCASF's local affiliates. The Council sponsored American teenagers at Artek, a Soviet summer camp on the Black Sea, as well as American college students studying at the Pushkin Institute in Moscow.
Part of the Council's program of cultural exchange was centered on the NCASF-sponsored Campaign for a Peoples' Peace Treaty, a broad-based attempt to involve communities, churches, and schools in the cause of American-Soviet friendship and disarmament. The Campaign, which lasted from 1985 until 1989, initiated a "People's Appeal for Peace." This peace petition, circulated in the Soviet Union and the United States, was intended for presentation to Ronald Reagan and Mikail Gorbachev; the Peoples' Peace Treaty ended unsuccessfully in 1987, when Reagan refused to accept the petition. The Campaign for a Peoples' Peace Treaty also initiated a project to "pair" American cities with Soviet cities of similar population and other characteristics. The Council only had mild success with this endeavor, while other organizations, such as Sister Cities International, paired many major US cities with Soviet cities.
The success and prominence of the NCASF vacillated throughout its history, often depending on the larger international political climate. The Council never returned to its significance during and immediately following World War II, but has occasionally been revived by the growing peace and disarmament movement. Throughout the late 1960s the Council's support dwindled, its base of support remaining with the Old Left. The Council lost much of it's Jewish support in the New York metropolitan area as a result of the Soviet pro-Palestinian position in the 1967 Arab-Israeli conflict.
Sequence of NCASF office holders: Chairmen
Corliss Lamont: 1943-1947
Reverend William Howard Melish: 1947-1951
John Kingsbury: 1949-1956
Rockwell Kent: 1957-1971
Reverend William Howard Melish: 1971-1978
Ewart Guinier: 1979-1984
John Cherveny: 1985-1987
John Randolph: 1988-1991
Executive Directors
Edwin Smith: 1944-1945
Reverend Richard Morford: 1946-1981
Reverend Alan Thomson: 1981-1991
Roy Kaufman: 1991
Related Archival Materials
The National Council for American-Soviet Friendship Film Collection, containing over 700 titles, is in the Academy Film Archive at the Pickford Center for Motion Picture Study in Los Angeles, CA.
For more information on Richard Morford, the Executive Director of the National Council of American-Soviet Friendship during 1946-1981, see the Richard Morford Papers (TAM 361).
The Collection of Soviet Union Photograph Albums and Photographs (PHOTOS 286) includes an untitled photograph album including photographs of members of the NCASF.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the National Council of American-Soviet Friendship span the years 1919-1990, with the bulk of materials ranging from 1943-1988. The collection consists mainly of correspondence, chiefly that of Richard Morford, minutes, and materials generated by the organization's activities, such as invitations, flyers, transcripts from speeches, records of planning meetings, and conference reports. The collection also includes materials pertaining to the Council's travel programs to the Soviet Union, administrative materials from the Campaign for a People's Peace Treaty (1985-1989), and materials from the NCASF's legal defense against the actions of the Subversive Activities Control Board. The collection provides good documentation of the NCASF's policy process and activities, but provides little documentation of the Council's positions on current events and its relationship with the USSR and the CPUSA.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Material
Two linear feet of published materials were transferred into the appropriate portions of the Tamiment Library. The following brief runs of various committee publications, spanning the years 1944-1948, were transferred to the serials:
News Bulletin-- Architects Committee: 1944-1945
The American Theatre-- Theater Committee: 1945-1946
Bulletin of the Committee on Education: 1945-1946
Science Bulletin-- Science Committee: 1945-1946
The Soviet Theatre-- Theater Committee: 1946
News Bulletin-- Building Industry Committee: 1946-1947
The Women Report-- Committee of Women: 1948
A 1984 biography of the Minnesota Council's founder, Cliff Herness, To Illuminate the Darkness, was transferred to the general library catalog.
Scrapbooks.; Correspondence.; Communist countries -- Tours.; Fliers (printed matter); Typescripts; Cold War.; Reports.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union -- Foreign Relations -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); United States |x Foreign relations |z Soviet Union.; Photographs.; Uphaus, Willard E. (Willard Edwin), 1890-1983.; Nearing, Scott, 1883-1983.; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995.; Campaign for a Peoples' Peace Treaty; Ward, Henry Frederick, 1873-1966.; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003; Van Kleeck, Mary, 1883-; Trachtenberg, Alexander, 1884-1966; Kingsbury, John (John Graham); Davis, Jerome, 1891-1979; Hunton, Alphaeus, 1903-1970; Nathan, Otto, 1893-1987; Fairchild, Henry Pratt, 1880-1956.; Melish, William Howard, 1910-; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Benson, Elmer Austin, 1895-1985.; Muste, A. J. (Abraham John), 1885-1967.; Du Bois, Shirley Graham, 1896-1977; Pepper, Claude, 1900-1989.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Refregier, Anton, 1905-1979; Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949; Smith, Jessica, 1895-1983; National Council of American-Soviet Friendship (U.S.); Strong, Anna Louise, 1885-1970; Thomson, Alan Craft, 1931-; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Morford, Richard, 1903-1986
- Series I: Administration, 1919-1990
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Administration (1919-1990), is divided into nine subseries.
  Subseries I: Organization and History (1940-1945), contains information about the organizations which preceded the NCASF, the Council's by-laws, and a chronology of its activities.
  Subseries II: Biographical Materials Regarding NCASF Associates (1941-1986), provides information on the personal achievements of the Council's most eminent leaders, officers, and supporters. This subseries also contains incomplete biographical information about some of the NCASF rank and file members.
  Subseries III: Minutes (1943-1990), contains the minutes of the Executive Council and Board of Directors, which have few gaps. The minutes for the National Board and for Membership Meetings are incomplete, spanning from 1975-1989 and 1945-1961 respectively. This subseries also contains minutes from Regional Meetings in 1977.
  Subseries IV: Internal Documents, Public Statements (1947-1989), contains reports, positions papers, and statements designated for press release. It also contains statements, resolutions, proposals, and reports meant for circulation within the NCASF. The materials in this subseries reflect the Council's position on some current events, including several unpopular Soviet actions and policies, and some organizational self-criticism.
  Subseries V: Correspondence (1919-1990), is arranged according to position in the organization's hierarchy: Chairmen, Secretary, Executive Directors, then general correspondence. Within each group, the correspondence is arranged chronologically. Most of the correspondence is among Council members and leaders of other progressive organizations, as well as with celebrities who sponsored the work of the NCASF. About half of the correspondence in this series is that of Richard Morford. Some prominent individuals with whom Morford corresponded were Governor Elmer Benson, Jerome Davis, Howard Fast, Shirley Graham DuBois, Alphaeus Hunton, A.J. Muste, Otto Nathan, Scott Nearing, Paul Robeson, Jessica Smith, editor of the New World Review, Anna Louise Strong, Alexander Trachtenberg, Mary Van Kleek, Harry Ward, and Max Weber. The Council's general correspondence contains letters from Senator Claude Pepper, Edward Stettinius, Henry Stimson, and Willard Uphaus. This subseries also contains a complete set of Alan Thomson's Fact Sheets to NCASF members, spanning the years 1981-1990.
  Subseries VI: Legal (1945-1989), is divided into two sections. The first section, Charters and Contracts, consists of only two folders, one of which is an agreement of cooperation with the USSR-USA Friendship Society. The second section, Defense of NCASF, contains all documents, petitions, depositions, statements, motions, proposed findings, correspondence with lawyers, and court transcripts pertaining to the actions of the Subversive Activities Control Board against the Council. It also contains documents pertaining to individual indictments of Council officers Morford, Lamont, and Kingsbury. Finally, this section contains material from the Alan Thomson Defense Fund, whose case is currently (1992) pending in court.
  Subseries VII: Members and Sponsors, Finances (1943-1988), contains early records of members and sponsors, many of whom joined the NCASF then severed their connections as a result of the SACB case against the Council. This subseries also contains sparse information regarding the Council's financing and fundraising programs.
  Subseries VIII: Committees and Local Councils (1943-1988), contains materials generated by the Council's various committees. The committees created the bulk of their documentation in the 1940's.
  The second section of this subseries, Local Councils, consists of materials generated by the various local branches of the Council in 25 cities and regions. Particularly active councils, such as those in Chicago and Southern California, have a substantial amount of material documenting their activities, while smaller or less active local councils, such as in Buffalo and Detroit, have little information. The activities of the local councils varied in scope, ranging from the presentation of Soviet films to testimonials honoring Soviet delegations and milestones in American-Soviet relations.
  Subseries IX: Publications and Educational Materials (1945-1985), documents the Council's creation and distribution of publications, development of Russian Language Classes, and circulation of Soviet films and documentaries. This subseries also documents Council-sponsored exhibits and contains a film catalog and bibliographies on the USSR. The NCASF designated most of these materials for distribution to local councils, trade unions, and schools.
  - Subseries I:A: Organization and History (1940-1945)
    - American Committee for Friendship with the USSR, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Congress of American-Soviet Friendship, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Salute to Our Russian Ally"--Congress of American-Soviet Friendship, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2.1)
    - American Council on Soviet Relations, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Revised By-Laws, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Committee on Reorganization, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "We Proudly Present: The Story of the NCASF", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chronology-NCASF Activities, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I:B: Biographical Materials Regarding NCASF Associates (1941-1986)
    - Kent, Rockwell-Activities, Shows, Speeches (by others), 1941-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Kent, Rockwell-Newsclippings, 1955-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kent, Rockwell-Articles, Speeches, Statements, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Kent, Rockwell-Obituary, Eulogies, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Kingsbury, John-Statements and Obituary, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lamb, Edward-Biographical Material, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lamont, Corliss-Articles, Speeches, Activities, 1939-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lamont, Corliss-Newsclippings, 1941-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Melish, William Howard-Biographical Material, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Morford, Richard-Articles, Addresses, 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Parsons, Howard-Curriculum Vitae, 1967-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Thomson, Alan--Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 1, Folder 18.1)
    - Ward, Harry F., 1945-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - List of Members-Biographical Statements, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Subseries I:C:: Minutes (1943-1990)
    - Executive Committee, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Executive Committee-Attendance Excuses, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Executive Committee-Memos, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Executive Committee-Progress Reports, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Executive Committee-Membership Lists, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Executive Board, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Executive Board-Report on Meeting, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Steering Committee, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Executive Board/Board of Directors, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Board Of Directors, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Board of Diectors, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Board of Directors, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Board or Directors, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Board of Directors, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Board of Directors, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Board of Directors, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Board of Directors, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Board of Directors, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Board of Directors, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Board of Directors, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Board of Directors, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Board of Directors, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Board of Directors, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Board of Directors, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Board of Directors, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Board of Directors, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Board of Directors, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Board of Directors, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Board of Directors, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Board of Directors, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Board of Directors, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Board of Directors, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Board of Directors, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Board of Directors, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - National Board, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - National Board--Executive Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - National Board--Executive Committee, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - National Board, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - National Board--Executive Committee, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - National Board, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - National Board--Executive Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - National Board--Executive Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - National Board--Executive Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Membership Meeting--Report, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Membership Meeting, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 65)